Guide to the Music Department Sheet music collection, 1827-1900 MS2136
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Music Department sheet music collection
1827-1900
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
George Washington University. Dept. of Music
MS2136
6 Linear Feet
Collection contains bound volumes of sheet music. These twelve items cover the years 1827-1900. The music includes piano and guitar pieces as well as music in French, Italian, English, and Spanish.
Restrictions on Access
Some records may be restricted.
Acquisition Information
These items were a gift of The George Washington University Music Department in 1994.
Collection Scope and Content
This collection contains bound volumes of sheet music. These twelve items cover the years 1827-1900. The music includes piano and guitar pieces as well as music in French, Italian, English, and Spanish.
Music -- History and criticism; Music; Songs; Sheet music; Mozart, Wolfgang Amadeus; Longfellow, Henry Wadsworth; Sousa, John Philip; Beethoven, Ludwig van; Foster, Stephen Collins; Chopin, Frédéric; Tennyson, Alfred Tennyson, Baron; Sullivan, Arthur, Sir
- Sheet music scrapbook 1, 1850-1873 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  General note
  Bound volume of numerous works, including: Beware! / words by H.W. Longfellow; composed by James Ernest Perring -- [several songs by Virginia Gabriel] -- When nobody's nigh to hear: ballad / words, Jean Inglow; music Fanny C. Shellman -- The battle field: fantasie brillante for the piano forte / dedicated to Gen. R.E. Lee by S.A. Strother -- Golden bells: caprice de concert / by Sydney Smith -- O hush thee my baby: quartet / by Arthur S. Sullivan. Carrie Brockett was the collector of this volume. Formerly Ind. Ms. Bd. 99 f
- Sheet music scrapbook 2, 1855-1885 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  Bound volume of 19 works, including: Marguerite / composed for the piano by James Ernest Perring -- Dreams of remembrance: a collection of beautiful songs -- Popular German songs with English and German words -- The bridge / written by H.W. Longfellow; music composed by M. Lindsay -- Answer: ballad / composed by A.G. Robyn -- Ruby: song / by Virginia Gabriel. Maggie Crumrine collected this volume. Formerly Ind. Ms. Bd. 98 f
- Sheet music scrapbook 3, 1859-1879 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  Bound volume containing 22 titles, including: Ellsworth requiem / George William Warren -- Pearls & diamonds: 12 melodies for the piano / by favorite composers -- The little gipsey: mazurka / George William Warren -- La scintilla mazurka / L.M. Gottschalk -- Remember me / Auguste Held -- Garibaldi's Sicilian march / H.N. Hempsted -- Cobweb tarentella / George William Warren. Annie Matilda Colt was the collector of this volume. Formerly Ind. Ms. Bd. 92 f
- Sheet music scrapbook 4, 1843-1872 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  Bound volume containing about 40 titles, including: The May Queen / poetry by Alfred Tennyson; music by William R. Dempster -- Moore's melodies. Number 1 / Thomas Moore -- My mountain home / poetry by Samuel Lover; music by William J. Wetmore -- Variations sur la marche favorite de l'opera de Bellini, la Norma / composee´s pour le piano forte par F. Hunten -- Selections from Fry's grand opera Leonora. Pt. I -- The snow storm, a ballad / the words by Seba Smith; music by L. Heath; arranged for the piano forte by George Hews -- [several polkas and waltzes]. Mrs. H. D. Cooke was the collector of this volume. Formerly Ind. Ms. Bd. 93 f
- Sheet music scrapbook 5, 1866-1900 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  Bound volume of numerous works, in English, French, Italian, and Spanish. Julia Clark Jesup was the collector of this volume. Formerly Ind Ms. Bd. 100 f
- Sheet music scrapbook 6, 1854-1870 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  Bound volume containing 30 titles, including: The last hope / L.M. Gottschalk -- The hundredth Psalm / transcribed for the piano forte by Wm. Vincent Wallace -- The banjo / L.M. Gottschalk -- Lotta's favorite waltz / Charles Kinkel -- Mendelssohns wedding march for two pianos / arranged expressly for the use of schools by A.W. Berg -- [several collections of favorite piano pieces]. Mary W. Nairn was the collector of this scrapbook. Formerly #94 f
- Sheet music scrapbook 7, 1852-1880 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  Bound volume containing numerous works, including: Sonate / W.A. Mozart -- The Japanese polka / by Gaston de Lille -- Diamond polka / composed by E. Szemele´nyi -- The swinging Schottisch / by Augustus Cull -- Oliver gallop / Tom, the blind Negro boy pianst -- Danse ne`gre / J. Ascher -- Plantation dance, burlesque / by J.N. Pattison -- Funeral march, to the memory of Abraham Lincoln / music by Mrs. E.A. Parkhurst. Titles and words in English, German, French and Italian. William Soule Stickney was the collector of this scrapbook. Formerly Ind Ms. Bd. 103 f
- Sheet music scrapbook 8, 1842-1855 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  Bound volume of numerous works, including: Jenny Lind's greeting to America -- New edition of Jenny Linds songs [We live mid the bounding] -- Gems of Madame Anna Bishop's concerts -- Songs of Madame Bishop / edited by N.C. Bochsa -- Little Red Riding Hood / words by Charles Jefferys; music by Stephen Glover -- The blind boy / poetry by Hannah F. Gould; music by William Dempster -- The cadets graduating song / words by a lady of the army; music by a cadet -- Graduating song, class of 1855, West Point. Lizzie Wheeler was the collector of this volume. Formerly Ind. Ms. Bd. 97 f
- Sheet music scrapbook 9, 1868-1898 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  Bound volume containing numerous works, especially waltzes and marches, including: Works for the pianoforte / Fre´de´ric Chopin -- Famous marches arranged for the piano -- The liberty bell march / by John Philip Sousa -- El capitan march / by John Philip Sousa -- The stars and stripes forever march / by John Philip Sousa. Some titles in French and Italian. Nannette Wurzburger was the collector of this volume. Formerly Ind Ms. Bd. 101 f
- Sheet music scrapbook 10, 1827-1839 ca. (Box 10, Folder 1)
  Bound volume containing numerous works, including: The lake of Como / G.A. Hodson -- collection of favorite songs arranged for the Spanish guitar / P.K. Moran -- New and improved method for the Spanish guitar / composed & arranged by Otto Torp -- [other pieces for the Spanish guitar]. Formerly Ind Ms. Bd. 95 f
- Sheet music scrapbook 11, 1843-1848 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  Bound volume of 20 works, including: Study with amusement: a series of progressive lessons / Franz Petersilea - instructions and progressive exercises in the art of singing / D. Crivelli -- The parlour quadrilles / Edward L. White -- Lucrezia Borgia Waltz / arranged by William C. Glynn -- Howard's quick step / Frank Howard -- Music of the original Christy Minstrels [Oh! Susanna! only] -- Grande sonate pathe´tique pour le piano forte / par Louis van Beethoven. Formerly Ind Ms. Bd. 96 f
- Sheet music scrapbook 12, 1859-1876 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  Bound volume of numerous works including: Don not turn me from your door / words and music by Will. S. Hays -- Sweet by and by / by J.P. Webster -- The heart bowed down / M.W. Balfe -- Embarrassment / by Frantz Abt -- Home sweet home / Henry R. Bishop -- Whispering hope / Alice Hawthorne -- Silver threads among the gold / words by Eben E. Rexford; music by H.P. Danks -- See that my grave is kept green / song and chorus written and composed by Gus. Williams -- Perished in the snow / words and music by Eddie Fox -- Close the shutters, Willie's dead! / words and music by Jas. E. Stewart. Formerly Ind Ms. Bd. 101 f